Hmm.
Not writing.
Okay, there we go.
Hmm. Okay.
I just have to hit that button every time.
Okay, it's 6:30. Can everyone hear me?
I can hear you.
Thank you, and my pen works
tonight, so no big technical difficulties.
Okay.
Welcome finally to
the space environment,
or the neutral environment.
Are there any questions for the folks that are on from last time?
Or homework one?
Okay.
We're going to start with the neutral environment this
week, and what do you think of, if someone online
wants to answer, or I'll give you a few minutes to
answer. What do you think of when you think the word neutral?
Anyone want to take a cut at that?
Besides some countries that are politically neutral.
Usually, it means
to most people, neither positive or negative, just kind
of neutral.
So, if there's nothing there, why do we care about the neutral
environment? Well, I'll tell you up front, the term we use for
neutral environment in
space environment situations is not really
neutral.
It's different from a vacuum. Neither can support
life,
but it still consists of stuff. It still consists of some
air
and particles that are both positive and
negative in some cases,
and has particles of sufficient density to cause
significant interaction, especially with things moving seven
kilometers per second or 16,000 miles per hour.
So we're going to look at four things today, and
to start off up front, I'm going to say the neutral environment is anything but
neutral.
It's very harsh up there. So we're going to look at aerodynamic
drag.
We're going to look at sputtering,
which is basically like sandblasting spacecraft.
Due to those neutral particles that aren't really neutral,
and charged particles.
Then we're going to look at the effects of atomic oxygen,
which
it is the most abundant source.
Wait a minute.
My computer got unplugged somehow.
There we go.
Atomic oxygen, which is the most abundant
element in many regions in space, and we'll study that later
tonight. And then spacecraft glow,
where light emitted by a gas
that is excited or ionized by solar radiation.
And we'll talk more about that later in today's lesson.
Shown here is the GOLD experiment launched in January
2018. It stands for Global Observation of the
Liminn Disc. The liminn is the edge of the
atmosphere, and the disc looks just like this
when viewed from the side. The Earth looks like a flat circle in the
atmosphere, a halo around it.
And of course, the Earth isn't flat.
Although there are some people who are adamant about saying that it
is.
It was intended to study the thermosphere and the ionosphere,
which is part of the thermosphere, and we will learn about the
later layers of the atmosphere tonight.
The formation of Earth's atmosphere.
What is an atmosphere? Anyone want to take a cut at that?
What is an atmosphere?
You all are quiet tonight. Okay. So, it's the layer of gas
that surrounds a celestial body,
and when the planets were formed,
atmospheres were mostly hydrogen and helium.
In phase one, the inner planets, Mercury, Venus,
Earth, and Mars, had high thermal speeds, and the solar
wind gave them atmospheric velocities
greater than the escape velocity from each planet.
So the lighter constituents, like hydrogen and helium, two of the most
lighter, were depleted.
Phase two is a young Earth. As Earth
started to cool, volcanic activity released
steam,
and that steam was
water, carbon dioxide, and ammonia.
And bacteria thrived on these two
constituents.
Bacteria thrived.
The surface was also being bombarded by comets and
asteroids.
On the other side, where we were
looking at the outer planets, we know that they retain much of their
hydrogen and helium, except for Pluto, which isn't a planet, by the way,
which had a lot of methane and molecular
nitrogen, and we're not sure why
And then here in phase three, which we're in now, we
have the ozone protecting us. We have oxygen,
we have carbon dioxide, we have
water,
and that came to bring
life to our planet.
So aeronomy is the study of the neutral environment.
50% of the atmospheric mass is in less
than 500 kilometers from the surface of the Earth.
75% is less than 11 kilometers.
And there's four main things that our
atmosphere does for us. It
keeps our atmosphere,
keeps our environment.
And the O2-CO2 cycle
near Earth's surface.
I'm even monitoring chat.
Oh, and if you want to type something into the chat, I'm also monitoring
that, so you don't have to answer out loud or ask a question out loud.
It redistributes the atmospheric
constituents.
I'll just abbreviate that there.
It absorbs energy from the sun, which helps keep
us not too hot or not too cold.
Because we talked last time about
how the Earth has that perfect rotation rate
that we don't burn up or freeze
when we're in the sunlight or when we're on
the opposite side. And it also
interacts
with our magnetic field.
And we said last time that the atmosphere started
at, or space started at about 230 kilometers, about
where a satellite will stay in orbit for a couple of orbits.
Most people define the line
between space and
airplanes, where airplanes can fly, as the
Karman Line, which is about 62 miles or 100 kilometers up.
So, we're not using that definition for the start of
space. We're using the definition where we are
in
the space environment
at about 230 kilometers.
So the terminology I'll use today is that
a sphere is the altitude bands,
troposphere, stratosphere, mesosphere, thermosphere, and
exosphere.
And then we'll call the pauses
the upper layer of each boundary.
So note the boundary can vary
by tens of kilometers, depending on the sun cycle and other
factors. So they're not all set at
50 miles where the mesosphere ends or anything like that.
Those can vary.
So what I wanted to do
is introduce each of those layers,
and we'll start with the troposphere,
down
here.
Lowest layer, obviously, and it goes up to
about 12 kilometers or seven miles
on average. At the tropics,
it can go up to 18 kilometers. At the equator, seven
kilometers, and at the poles, it's much less
prominent,
up to six kilometers.
It consists, of course, of 78%
nitrogen
and 21% oxygen,
and
the rest is made up of small constituents like
carbon dioxide and
argon, et cetera.
All weather takes place and originates here.
75% of the atmosphere is contained here, and
the temperature ranges from 20 degree C to minus
50 degree C, or 68 Fahrenheit to
minus 60 Fahrenheit, depending on where you are on the
Earth and what altitude you're at,
and it is characterized by
density and temperature decreasing with altitude.
That's pretty standard in the troposphere.
Less than 3% is water vapor.
Okay, the stratosphere
Is from 11 to 12 kilometers to 50
kilometers or 7 to 31 miles. It's
drier and even less dense.
It has the same composition except for here
we have the ozone,
O3.
At 10 to 80 kilometers, again, depending on sun cycles and other
variables, most commercial airlines
are in the troposphere or the stratosphere.
Some high-flying airplanes can do the stratosphere, not many.
And some birds can get up that high, but again, not many.
Most aircraft and commercial airlines fly in
the troposphere or the boundary between the two.
There's little turbulence because it has
isothermal properties.
Little water vapor,
and the upper boundary is not well-defined due to the
absorption of the UV rays, and it's highly dependent on the sun cycle.
It can vary from minus 50 degrees Celsius to minus
15 degrees Celsius at the top, which is getting colder.
That's minus 60 Fahrenheit to five degrees Fahrenheit.
Balloons can fly that high. We regularly fly balloons from
UCCS to 120,000 feet.
And clouds.
Most clouds are located in the stratosphere or the
troposphere, so some clouds can get up there.
The mesosphere.
It is also called the ignorosphere,
nicknamed that,
because we really don't know that much about it because it's
too high for aircraft to fly and too low for
spacecraft to fly. High-altitude balloons can't make it up that
high. At 50 miles or about 80
kilometers is where it starts. This is the
coldest layer
at minus 93 degrees Celsius to minus 50 degrees
Celsius. In Fahrenheit, that would be minus
135 to minus 60.
Some high-altitude clouds can form in that region, but
most meteoroids burn up there, and that's
where you see your
shooting stars.
Then we reach the Karman Line, where technically spacecraft
can begin flying in space.
That is the thermosphere, which goes from 80 to
708 kilometers, so that contains low Earth orbit.
So we have the ISS
there. Ozone is rapidly destroyed by
chemical reactions. So the O3 forms
into atomic oxygen, and that will
combine with pretty much anything.
Temperature increase varies from minus
93 Celsius to 1,500 degrees Celsius.
The minus 3 obviously would be in the eclipse,
and the 1,500 degrees Celsius would be in direct sunlight.
So you can get huge temperature differences there.
Fortunately, you don't stay in either the
eclipse or the sun
side very long. The ISS, for example, only takes 90
minutes to get around the Earth. So it's dominated
by these constituents. It's dominated by oxygen,
nitrogen, helium, and
hydrogen. And helium starts becoming
prominent at about 650 kilometers,
and hydrogen starts becoming prominent at
2,500 kilometers.
Auroral phenomena occur here. That air glow and the
pretty colors that it makes in the side,
in the sky, and it includes the ionosphere, which is
coming up in just a minute. I'll talk about that.
That includes a couple of regions here, so that's why it's
later in this lecture.
And again, ISS and most LEO satellites are in
that region. Then we reach the
exosphere, 700 to 800 kilometers,
and everything above that, so that would include
GEO.
And it consists mostly of atomic
oxygen again,
helium
and hydrogen.
Helium starts prevailing again about
anything above 650 kilometers and
2,500 kilometers like I briefed just a while ago.
Now, what is the ionosphere? The ionosphere goes from
about 80 to 600 kilometers or 50 to
360 miles. It's in a region of the
thermosphere,
mesosphere, exosphere.
But we consider it a little different because that is the ionized
part of the upper atmosphere that was
ionized due to solar radiation. It
influences radio propagation, and it allows
radio waves to get to distant
places. We will discuss this in more detail in some
later plasma lessons. It is
consisted of different layers D, E,
and F layers and one of the lower D levels disappears at
night, which is why ham radio operators get
more distance at night because it's bouncing off of the
ionosphere at a higher altitude.
Temperature, again, can range from extreme temperatures,
minus 720 degrees C to 2,000 degrees C,
or,
minus 1,330 degrees Fahrenheit to 3,600
degrees Fahrenheit.
And then I had one more introduction
or one more region.
We have the homosphere
and heterosphere.
And it is a well-mixed region, less
than the atmosphere, the homosphere, less than the atmosphere of the turbopause
up to about 100 kilometers, the Karman Line.
It's the lower portion of the thermosphere, and again, it's
characterized by nitrogen and oxygen, and it's mixed by
convection and due to turbulence and
winds in that region.
The heterosphere is above the turbopause, so below
turbopause.
Greater than turbopause. Oops, can't spell it.
And at higher altitudes, it's dominated by hydrogen and
helium.
Hydrogen
tends to dominate during solar min.
Atomic oxygen tends to dominate towards
solar max. So pending any questions about that,
I'm going to move on and talk about one of the
major factors
in
low Earth orbit, aerodynamics
forces.
So let's take a small portion of the
atmosphere
and
we'll call it a parallel pipet because I didn't draw that really straight,
of height dh
in hydrostatic equilibrium. So
we have a pressure here.
We have a pressure plus
a differential pressure
due to the height.
And here we've got P plus dh again.
And we should define a coordinate system. We'll define this x and y.
I have left a force off of there. That is
mg, always still acting.
Where A is defined as the
cross-sectional area.
H is obviously the height.
P is pressure.
And the area is in meters squared. The height is in meters.
Pressure is a unit of force,
newtons.
And density, I'll differentiate by putting a little o at the bottom.
That is rho
is density
in kilogram per meter
cubed.
So if we sum forces in the y direction,
we've got pressure times
area
minus P plus, and I'm doing this for
a reason, dP over dh times
dh
times area minus mg.
And if it's in equilibrium, that's all got to equal zero.
And we might recognize that mass is
density times area times the
height times... or mg,
let me correct that,
times g.
So we get Pa minus Pa
minus dPa
minus
what I just said mass was equal to, rho naught
or rho
area dhg, and
that's all got to equal zero. So these two terms cancel,
all the areas drop out. So we get
dP
is
minus the density
times dh
times g.
So I'm going to call that equation one.
So let me know if I'm going too fast through this for you to catch
up.
I am recording this, though, but so you can always go back and look at it.
Now let's review the ideal gas law
So the ideal gas law says PV
= nRT.
So we're doing a little review of chemistry here.
We'll say M is the molar mass.
Kilogram
per kilomole,
and m is the mass of gas.
And n is defined as that
ratio, which becomes... Whoops, the mass would be
in kilograms, obviously.
Mass of the gas divided by
the molar mass
or number of kilomole.
And R is the universal gas constant,
which we will use R is
8314.472
joules per kilomole
Kelvin.
So from this, we know pressure is
nRT divided
by volume. Oh, I forgot to put
that.
And that would generally be in meters cubed.
And that is equal to m divided by big M,
RT over V.
And you might recognize if I rewrite it like this, m over
V, RT over M, you might
recognize that as the density.
So pressure is the density
times RT over M.
So if I solve for the density, we get
PM over RT.
So that is how the ideal gas law is involved in this.
So I will call this equation two.
So going on to the next page, we've got
a repeat equation one. We have dP is
minus rho naught
is equal to... Whoops.
That's not what I meant. dP is minus rho
naught
dhg. That's what we said from before.
So dP using equation two
is minus PM over RT
gdh.
Now, if we integrate this from P
naught
to P, that would be an initial pressure or pressure at C level,
dP over P
is equal to minus the integral
from zero to h,
mg over RT
dh.
We will define a constant
called the scale factor.
And we're going to let that equal to RT over
mg. And depending on what region you're in,
temperature could be considered constant.
That is what we're going to consider it in the lower region.
Temperature is about constant.
This is officially called the scale height, not the scale factor.
So the integral of dP over P is the natural log
of P
is equal to minus one over h
times h.
So that simplifies it a little bit.
We can solve this, and I'm not going to go through the details
of the solution.
We've got pressure is equal to rho naught.
That becomes the integration constant, E to
the minus h over h.
Oops.
Went to the next page way too soon.
And that is equation three.
So if we take-- Let's rewrite that equation
here.
So if we take h equals
one
of the scale heights,
we get P equals density
times E to the minus one,
which becomes about
0.368,
the density at C level.
If we let H equals 2H, rho
is density
E to the minus 2
or 0.135
sea level density.
So forth and so on. If we take 3H P equals
density E to the minus 3,
which reduces rapidly because we're
decreasing this by an exponential factor
each time. So that's 0.050 rho naught.
So the bottom line is that the
pressure decreases rapidly with altitude.
And just a reminder, density at sea level is
101.3 kilopascals
or 14.69
psi,
pounds per square inch.
Now, this works really well for the homosphere
portion of our atmosphere.
So what does that look like? Well,
it looks like the
graph on the left
and
you'll notice this only goes up to about 30 kilometers.
To 30 kilometers on this slide. This equation is good
for only less than 100 kilometers.
After that, it gets much more complex.
And satellites can't even fly that low.
And
I meant to say this is pressure at sea level,
not density.
So that's the bottom line. It's pretty well predictable,
less than 100 kilometers, but once you get above that,
pressure becomes much less predictable,
especially during high and low solar cycles.
So the aerodynamic force, you may recall from
previous classes or you may be seeing it for the first time here,
is minus one half density coefficient of drag,
area times velocity squared. That's
actually a dot product there, which
since we're all dealing in the same direction becomes velocity
squared. So we will let this equal to velocity squared.
A is the frontal area.
Rho we just discussed.
And this is a huge effect up to about
1,000 kilometers.
I think the textbook refers to it, or the
Tribble reference refers to it up to 1,200 kilometers,
but at 1,200 kilometers it takes a very long time for
something to de-orbit.
What further complicates this is that the density is highly
dependent on solar activity, and these were
predictions of
solar maxes for the last few years.
Now, Cycle 24 ended up being a
little less than we expected. Cycle 25 turned
out to be much higher than we predicted.
And also note that the scale height
varies with temperature and we can get some of those huge temperature
variations in the upper parts of the atmosphere.
So our model that we derived from this
page really isn't good for satellite modeling at all.
So how do we get this drag coefficient?
These are some examples. That's the coefficient of drag.
The air is moving in,
relative velocity is
moving in that direction, the air velocity.
So if we're going in
the velocity direction here,
that is how drag affects us
for all of these. And you can see that the hollowed-out
shell there, and these are dots.
1.4, it came out wrong in the
textbook that I copied this from.
You can see that a typical satellite, which would be a square satellite,
isn't represented on here, but it would be
about
1.2 coefficient of drag.
So those are some examples. Now in astrodynamics, we're going to take
this factor and call
it
ballistic coefficient, and we're going to define that as mass over
CDA.
So that
opposite from what is shown here, you would have
a high ballistic coefficient for a
very streamlined object and
a very
low ballistic coefficient for a blunt object.
So this is how we would depict this.
For a high ballistic coefficient, we would have an attached shock
wave, which for missiles we don't really care about.
But for a low ballistic coefficient, if you've ever wondered why
the return capsules come in with the bottom
up or the bottom down,
that's because that creates a detached shock wave,
so you have some air molecules in between here,
and it doesn't burn up the atmosphere.
Whereas this
high ballistic coefficient-- Whoops.
How did it get that big?
I did not mean to do that.
Yep, not that small.
Okay.
For a low ballistic coefficient, the shock wave is detached.
This would also represent high deceleration.
Low ballistic coefficient would result in lower temperature,
not low, but lower, and lower
deceleration, so that when there's people inside, they don't get
burnt up or subjected to high G-forces that would kill
them.
So let's talk about the effect of
drag on orbits.
So if we're initially in the green orbit,
this is how drag would affect it. Basically, we're going this way,
so it basically applies a reverse delta
V opposite the direction of
travel.
That takes away the potential energy mostly.
It does affect perigee a little bit, but mostly apogee is
where the energy reduction comes from.
So what does this do to our satellites in orbit?
Well, the semi-major axis would go down.
Eccentricity, you can see as it moves further
in, becomes more and more circular,
so the eccentricity would go down.
Our total specific mechanical energy would go down because
a's going down.
However, our potential energy,
well, is also going down. However, our
kinetic energy, because velocity increases
like the factor mu over r,
if it's circular, of course, it's a little more complicated equation
if you've taken astrodynamics than that,
increases. So the kinetic energy actually increases
with more drag, which increases that velocity term.
Let's go back to that.
Here, that velocity squared term, which increases your
drag. So you have a couple of non-linear
effects going on here.
So that's the basic effect of drag.
And the swelling of the Earth's atmosphere due to the
sun's
cycles can make that even
worse.
Okay. So
I wanted to go through,
and I have an example that I'm going to do
for your-- This is actually your first homework problem.
By the way, the first homework problem usually will
be a recap of or review. You provide
a review of the current events presentations.
We didn't have one this week, so this is actually problem number
one.
So given this
equation, which is a decent model
of the density up to about
1,000 kilometers,
covering most of the LEO satellites that we have up
there. We have 100-kilogram satellites
with an effective cross-sectional area of one meter squared.
It's in a circular Earth orbit at an altitude of 400
kilometers, and its drag coefficient is 2.2.
So you're going to estimate the satellite's lifetime.
So here's the process for doing that.
Let me get
my solution here out. We're going to
start with this expression,
and we're going to use the expression for velocity
for a circular orbit
to find an expression for total energy.
This is total energy because it has mass in it.
It's not specific mechanical energy.
So E equals one-half m
mu over r
minus mu over r.
Combining the denominator,
2r
mu minus 2mu,
all times mass.
We get the total energy is
Minus M mu over 2r.
Okay, that's step one. We have an expression for energy
in terms of M, mu, and r.
Now, we have to review our calculus and remember
the,
what was it called? The chain rule.
So to find dE over dt,
we can't just use dE over dr. Remember, dE is a
function of r. We have to add in
dr over dt to get dE
over dt.
So,
if we take this expression, energy
is minus
M mu over 2r,
I can differentiate that,
and I get M mu over
2r squared dr over
dt.
So, in terms of
the rate of change of our altitude, where
r is equal to the radius of the Earth
plus altitude,
we get
M mu over 2r squared. And when I
use a dot,
that always represents the derivative with respect to time.
Okay, so remembering that expression, that's going to be
important here.
We're going to use another expression of energy
loss due to the drag force. So,
we are going to say dE over
dt is minus one-half
coefficient of drag
A velocity cubed, because it's F dot D.
That is the derivative of energy over time.
And we said that was equal to M mu over
2r squared
r dot.
So r dot
is equal to minus one-half
rho CDA
mu over r
to the three halves
times
two, whoops,
2r squared over M mu.
So r dot, remembering that that's dr over
dt.
Combining all that
and
combining the mu terms and the r
terms,
the twos cancel out, by the way.
We get minus rho CDA
over M square root of mu
r.
Go downstairs and turn the tunes down.
Just couldn't you call me or something?
I did.
All right.
Okay. And that is your expression for
r dot.
All right, now how are we going to use that?
Now,
this is not easy to differentiate.
I would recommend doing it by a computer,
but we are going to do it by hand by
assuming a reasonable value for r.
So, I'm going to let r be an average at
this point, big assumption,
of 275 kilometers.
So dr over dt
is the density
times the coefficient of drag,
the area
over the mass,
square root of mu
kilometers
cubed per second squared times r, which
is the radius of the Earth, 6,378 kilometers
plus 278
kilometers.
So dr over dt is, if you work out
all the math there for the constants,
it becomes minus
1.139 times 10 to the
minus 8 kilometers
squared per
meter second times
1,000
Meters, because we have to convert to meters.
Kilometers
squared.
And that constant equals to minus
0.01133
meters per second.
So that's meters per second. That's not too bad.
But
we can now take this
as the difference in r,
so r final minus r
initial, if I integrate that. Well, let's write it out.
Integral of r,
or dr from,
let's see, what was our original altitude?
to 100.
Oops.
Original was 400. We're going to 150,
is equal to minus
0.01133
dt
from t naught to t, and that will give us our time to deorbit.
So we end up with minus
250,000
meters divided by minus
0.01133, rounded off greatly,
is 22,600
and
805, 15 seconds,
or delta t is about
255 days.
Which is actually
pretty quick decay.
And you can see how this happens rapidly.
So how can you make this more accurate?
Well, first off, density isn't constant.
So use a density function. That's why I gave it to
you.
That is a function of altitude.
And also,
r varies
as a function of time.
Time.
And you could also consider that as a function of altitude.
So
that is what you're going to do in homework problem one.
Cross-sectional area, we went through all that, but you're
going to use this density function as a function of altitude, and
you also have to take into account that r varies with time.
Estimate the satellite altitude, do the same thing.
When you redeem your points at the pump.
As a function of altitude, and
you will get a smaller number, actually.
You should get a smaller number if you do it correctly, and you should
get a r graph that looks something
like this
over time.
Because as you get lower in the atmosphere, again, velocity increases and the
density increases.
So,
any questions about that?
And that was, again, problem one.
And let's see.
None from me.
Okay. I was looking in the chat. I don't see any questions in the
chat. Okay. So that should get you started on-
Probably develop some over time here, but not at the moment.
Okay, thanks.
Totally.
So that should get you started on homework problem one.
Homework problem, and this would be two.
In homework problem one, how much drag makeup
fuel is needed for the spacecraft in problem one to
maintain its original orbit for one year?
We're going to assume an average solar cycle conditions in monopropellant
fuel with an Isp of 200 seconds,
and that is specific impulse,
which is a measure of
rocket efficiency.
And I'll walk you through how to do this.
So,
recall
force of drag is
one half rho
CDAV squared.
So let's draw a free body diagram of this.
We've got a thrust force
and a drag force
And let's say my satellite is moving in that direction, so we'll call that
direction positive X.
We're going to assume
the spacecraft
has a dry mass
of M,
and fuel mass
of Mp,
and it's moving
in a circular orbit again, so at a
constant
velocity
of V nought.
In order
to counter the drag force,
we would have to expend fuel.
So fuel is expelled
from the spacecraft
at a constant velocity, VP.
Okay, so I'll give you a moment to catch up there.
And we're going to start with Newton's second law, which we went over last time.
It is not F equals ma. In fact, the F equals ma term
goes away in this case because we're moving
at a constant velocity.
And I just realized I have to add in another sheet
here, so give me a moment to do that.
Maybe a couple of slides.
Go back to slideshow from current
slide.
Okay,
so here we go. Newton's second law:
sum of forces is equal to
the change of momentum over time, and we said
last time that was equal to
dMp over
dt times velocity
plus mass of the propellant, dVP
over dt, where VP
is a constant or a vector,
and that term is the one that goes to zero in this
case.
So F thrust
equals F drag
for equilibrium,
and we get that's equal to dMp
over dt,
VP.
And I'll drop the vector notation because everything is going in
the positive x direction.
Okay, cool.
So F drag,
I'll call that delta t,
is equal to Mp dot
VP,
is equal to F thrust.
How much longer are you doing this? Because it's like, you know.
Hold on.
You've had all day to do this.
I'd like a little quiet and enjoy relaxation now.
Sorry about that. I lost my work there, so I will go back
over it again.
You get that, Crop?
Knock him off.
Oh,
no. Stop. Leave him rest.
He's dead.
So since we have a constant velocity, that term goes to zero.
So F drag
delta T-
You sure?
... is equal to F thrust-
Right
... delta T
is equal to Mp dot VP.
And I'm going to pause for just a minute and move to another room.
Why you always harping on me?
Dog. Oh, you understand this distance is... You don't recall.
Okay.
So specific impulse.
Let me get back to my chart here
Let me get back to my chart here.
At the same time?
Okay, it's not letting me go back to full screen.
Oh, well.
Hold on. Well.
Oh.
So we got an expression for M.p. Now, specific impulse-
Got it
... is a commonly used measure for the efficiency of rockets.
And it's defined as thrust
over
the mass
times
the gravitational constant.
So F thrust
is equal to Isp
Mp.g
is... Oops, that was mass flow rate.
Mp.vp,
and that is equal to the force of
drag. So we're basically using that force
to counteract the drag.
So here we can see VP is
Isp times g.
So moving on to one last page.
Mp dot
is F drag
over VP
over Ispg.
So now we have an expression for the mass that
changed,
I'll call it delta Mp over
delta T,
is equal to F drag
over Ispg.
So the change in mass or how much mass you used
is just equal to F drag
delta T over
Ispg.
Oh, that.
So that should get you started on homework problem
two.
Well.
And that is the end of part one slides.
Let me move on to part two.
Yeah.
No doubt.
Cool.
That's all.
Sergeant.
Where's the rest of the 13?
Okay.
Where it is?
So can you all see my slides? Just give a thumbs up or put it in the
chat if you can see my slides. Yeah, we can see them.
Okay, cool.
All right.
Simple.
So the neutral environment part two, we're going to look at some design
considerations.
And what we learned in the last section
was the neutral environment
and the layers of the Earth's atmosphere and something about
drag.
This time, in this section, we're going to look at atomic
oxygen effects, which causes a change or reduction
in material thickness, and we're also going to consider
spacecraft glow.
So before we do that, we're going to do a quick quiz, not graded,
but just for fun,
and we're going to see how much we remembered from the last time.
Okay.
So I'll go through these first, jot down your answers,
and then we'll go back over them. So which of the following orbits would be
affected the most by Earth's atmospheric drag?
Circle.
Okay, so jot down your answer here.
You are not.
Yes. That's right. Damn it.
And I have one answer in the chat that looks correct.
Which object would have the largest coefficient of drag if
the object is moving to the right?
And I'll give you a hint. It's the one with that most spacecraft
have,
the
object or the shape that most spacecraft have.
Tall
and close.
Okay. Moving on to the next one. Which would have the
largest ballistic coefficient?
To overload the boy.
I don't want him.
Which way is the front?
Which way is the front? Okay. Hmm. See some good
answers in the chat.
All around. You don't travel.
Moving on.
Perfectly.
Which of the following, and we did go over this.
Which of the following is true about a drag's energy on a orbit's total
energy potential and kinetic energy?
So we just went over that.
So.
It was boring.
I can go to tech school? Tech school?
No. Never even seen the inside of a tank. I'm a clerk typist.
Head of the Fifth Corps HQ, they're pulling me off the truck. They're sending me.
Goddamn sight.
And which of the COEs are affected, that's
supposed to be affected by drag, and how?
How? Mug songs. How? Okay. I set
up. Go on.
You a praying man?
Go to church?
Bishop nominational.
Episcopal?
Okay.
You are your main line, aren't you? Yeah.
I am. Are you saved?
From that, then?
Okay, got some good answers in the chat.
Number six, in which atmosphere layer is the Earth's
ozone?
Say you.
Say what?
Thank you, everyone.
Oh, in five Gs, come take a look at your seat.
That's where you're going to be.
Get a bucket of hot water from the kitchen and get that laid.
Okay, got a lot of different answers here.
Be interesting when I go back over them.
Okay,
quiz question seven.
Which of the Earth's atmospheric layers is nearly isothermal?
Okay, moving on to question eight.
In this class, we consider space to begin at the Karman Line.
True or false?
Okay, got a couple of different answers here, too.
Atomic oxygen is relatively stable above the stratosphere.
It is not very much with the sun's cycle.
Who's that? If this bike takes off, one comes back, it's
either vaporized or what?
Four.
Okay, we got a couple of different answers here, too.
And then finally, quiz question number 10.
Which of the Earth's atmospheric layers is the coldest?
And we talked about that.
And we got at least one good answer or a couple of good answers here.
All right, so let's go back over these.
Let's start with number one. The correct answer to number one is
indeed the ISS or C.
Cut. Who's that? Picture.
Number two, the correct answer is D, which is the shape.
Unfortunately, most spacecraft are
formed in,
but it's very hard to put things internally into
spherical objects or
slanted objects.
Largest ballistic coefficient would be the one that's most
streamlined.
Need two. What?
The correct answer to number four is E decreases,
PE decreases, KE increases. So that would be
D.
The correct answer to these are B and D.
Both semi-major axes and eccentricity decreases.
In which layer is the Earth's ozone?
That would be the mesosphere.
You see that?
He's an SS. Kill every last one of you, can't you?
Nearly isothermal, the correct answer is the
stratosphere.
Boy, take me that gun.
Number eight is false. We said about 230
kilometers.
You.
And this is also false. Atomic oxygen is very
dependent on the sun's solar cycle.
And then the coldest is the mesosphere.
Oh, yeah. Now.
Okay, so that was kind of fun to go through, and it's
not part of your grade, so that's why it was fun
Okay. So
since space has a very low density of gases,
most fluid equations and theories
are based on a medium. So
we must review basic atmosphere physics or the kinetic
theory of gas. So reviewing the gas laws,
we get P is pressure, V is volume, obviously.
We went through this before. N is
little m over big M. R is the
universal gas constant, and temperature is the
temperature in Kelvin.
So you can calculate the number of moles of the gas, and you have a homework
problem on this.
And then next, we have Dalton's law of partial
pressures. So each gas in a mixture exerts a partial
pressure equal to the pressure it would exert if it were the only
gas present in the volume. So the partial pressure
or the total pressure
is equal to pressure for
gas one, pressure of gas two,
et cetera,
where
the PIs or the P1s and P2s and P3s is
called the partial
pressure
of constituent.
And P is obviously the total
pressure.
And since
the individual pressures is equal to nI RT
over V,
we get P is the summation of all those
pressures
is equal to the summation of nI
RT over V.
And I can rewrite that, bring out the constant.
nRT over V,
sum of nI over n. So notice the
ns cross out.
So P is equal to, we'll
write this a little differently,
nRT over V
summation over all of
X, where Xi is nI over
n.
So the individual pressures are equal
to Xi P, where of course I equals
one, two, three, et cetera.
And we'll do an example in just a minute.
And then finally, Avogadro's law says this:
equal volumes
of gases
at the same temperature
and
pressure
contain the same number of molecules,
regardless
of their chemical nature
and physical properties.
So a mole
fraction
of a gas is equal to its volume fraction,
is what Avogadro's law
says.
So Xi, we said was nI over
n, but according to this law, it is
also equal to Vi over V, where
V is the summation of all the volumes.
So we'll do an example. Given a sample gas has a pressure of
6.34 atmosphere consisting of 1.39
total moles of which 0.5 is nitrogen, determine the
partial pressure of nitrogen.
So we know the pressure is 6.34
atmospheres,
1.39 moles total
Of which
0.5 moles
is nitrogen.
So we get the partial pressure is 0.5
over 1.39 times
6.34 atmospheres is
equal to 2.28
atmosphere
of
N2.
I'm
a little bit ahead of myself there.
Okay. Example two: Determine the molar mass of
the atmosphere of the Earth at sea level, and we know
the main constituents of that.
So we've got oxygen is
21%,
nitrogen is 78.1%,
and argon,
and there's others, but these are the main ones,
0.9%.
So the question is
determine the molar mass of the atmosphere at sea level.
So we're going to take this step by step.
We got the oxygen, we'll call it O2,
is 0.21
times two molecules times
15.999, which is the
atomic mass of oxygen.
Is equal to 6.7196
kilogram per kilomole.
Nitrogen would then be 0.781
times two molecules times
14.007 or
21.86 or
kilogram per kilomole.
And then argon is then
0.009 times one, only one mole
and molecule of that, times
39.948
or
0.3595
kilogram per kilomole.
So if you add all that up,
the total
is
28.958
kilogram per kilomole.
Or you could convert that to grams per kilomole.
Okay, so that should help you with homework problem three.
The Apollo command module has a volume of 5.9 cubic meters
and its atmosphere is 100% oxygen at a pressure of
five psi and temperature of 21
degrees C.
So determine the mass of oxygen
present.
So I'll give you some hints.
You would start with pressure is five
psi
times
1.01325, the
pressure at sea level
in per meters cubed
over 14.7
psia.
And use the relationship PV equals
NRT
to get
N.
You can solve that for N. You've got V, you've got
RT, and you're solving for N.
And then
Big
M would be equal to two times what we said before for
oxygen.
And then m would be equal to N times
m, and that would give you your total mass in kilograms.
So any questions about what we've done so far?
I don't see anything in the chat, so
we'll go ahead and move on.
So we said last time the Earth's atmosphere was...
We went through last time how the Earth's atmosphere was formed,
what layers, and what they consist of.
And we said that helium and hydrogen were lost into
space due to high temperatures,
insufficient gravity to keep them in the Earth's gravitational field,
and the solar wind.
These are the main constituents of Earth's atmosphere.
We've been talking about nitrogen and oxygen and argon, but there are
other constituents.
And just to note, it's interesting how small carbon dioxide makes up,
but we use that as our main measure of
lack
of environmental greenhouse effect, which I think is kind of
interesting. Anyway, just pointed that out.
Another view of Earth's atmosphere is the homosphere and
heterosphere, which we talked about before.
And homosphere goes up to about 100 kilometers or the
Karman Line.
And this also shows where the thermopause is
and the heterosphere is.
In the homosphere, we get uniformity in concentration of
gases,
pretty much due to turbulence and wind.
There is some non-uniformity in the ozone layer due to
variation of water vapor with altitude.
And in the heterosphere, you get a
significant variation in composition as a function
of altitude
due to the absence of mixing at those altitudes.
The number density of each constituent falls
off nearly exponentially with increasing altitude.
So O2 and N2, which have higher mass, fall more
rapidly than hydrogen and helium.
So the higher altitude constituents are going to be
helium,
hydrogen, and atomic oxygen.
During solar min,
atomic hydrogen dominates.
It gets broken apart due to the Sun's radiation.
And then in solar max,
in this region,
atomic oxygen dominates,
again, due to charged particles and the Sun's
UV effects breaking those particles apart.
This is information about... Oh, this is one I just
went over.
You can see during solar max and solar min which
constituents
govern or
are prominent in those regions.
Okay, so the planetary atmosphere, the outer
gaseous planets are relatively thick atmospheres.
Inner terrestrial planets are relatively thin.
So that's a relative type of comparison,
not
necessarily
compared to anything other than a relative comparison.
So there's five main means
of loss of planetary atmosphere.
We have the
thermal
escape
and bombardment, atmospheric cratering,
condensation, and chemical reactions.
And the thermal escape means that lower mass
constituents
or particles
can
overcome
the gravitational pull of the Earth,
or in general terms, the planet.
So those hydrogen and helium atoms are gone.
Bombardment means the
impacts
by extraplanetary particles
can increase.
And what that does is we get the atmospheric thermal
velocity and breakup. Heavier molecules are broken into lighter
atoms and molecules so they can escape.
So
what you're seeing here is a depiction of that, where those
hydrodynamic escape particles are departing from
a planet, just a representative planet,
and
that happens. Atmospheric cratering means
large impacts on surface, which fortunately we don't get much
of,
but other planets do.
Impart
sufficient
energy
to allow
atmospheric
Constituents
I am not trained in machine gun dead bodies. I'm trying my very best.
To
escape.
Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune
were formed much closer than they are today, and they started to
creep toward their present locations about 4.5 billion years
ago,
and
they scattered some debris, which some of it came our way.
Condensation means atmospheric
constituents condense on the planet's surface.
Sorry,
dog.
Interestingly
enough,
Pluto's atmosphere, which is not a planet, has more than
doubled since 1988 because it has a lot of
nitrogen ice, and as it warms, the atmospheric
pressure increases up to 80%
when the temperature increases by one degree Celsius.
And then finally, we have the chemical reactions that
occur, and we get atmosphere combining-
Why's he
here? You know why he's here?
He's here to kill you. He's here to talk to you.
He's here to rip your throat out.
With material on the surface.
You here to get me killed?
You going to get me killed?
So, for
example, xenon and krypton on Mars are abundant.
It has a lot of isotopes or with different numbers of
neutrons formed in the regolith, and the cosmic
rays penetrate that.
So they lose one or more
neutrons. Atoms of xenon pick up the neutrons, or neutron
capture, and they form xenon-124 and
xenon-126.
Bromine, plus the cosmic rays, form krypton-80
and krypton-82.
So the isotopes enter the atmosphere when
surface impacts and abrasion occur.
So, in summary, for thermal escape, the average
speed of the constituent gases are
less than one-tenth the escape velocity,
where the escape velocity, oops, Esc,
is equal to square root of two mu over
r plus E.
At a very large distance, remember at the edge of the Earth's sphere of
influence,
energy goes to zero, so we get the escape
is square root of two mu over r,
where r is
6378 kilometers
plus the atmospheric height.
And recall mu is
398600.5
kilometer cubed per second squared,
which is g times the mass of the Earth.
This is a gross oversimplification because the
effect of the solar wind is not considered here.
So, how do planets gain their atmospheric gases?
Example, how do you form an oxygen-rich atmosphere without life?
Earth has life, obviously,
and especially with red dwarfs, which
70% of our stars in our Milky Way galaxy are red
dwarfs, and much smaller stars emit
large solar flares, and that strips atmosphere of
nearby planets, and then they emit less UV
light.
So we have high carbon to nitrogen
ratios. A runaway greenhouse starts with
carbon dioxide and O2.
Water forms, we've got H2O, which forms
O2 in the upper atmosphere,
and then for dry
constituents, we have oxygen, nitrogen, and carbon
dioxide.
For atmospheric cratering and outgassing,
we have large impacts on the surface that impart sufficient
energy to allow constituents to escape,
which I said in the last chart.
We also get outgassing, where volcanoes
emit
water, carbon dioxide, nitrogen, hydrogen
sulfide, and sulfur dioxide
Let me see. There.
So, we also get
planetary atmospheric loss. We get evaporation and
sublimation, where evaporation is obviously liquid to gas,
and sublimation is solid to gas.
And we also get
bombardment,
where Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune, the gas giants, have a lot of
hydrogen, helium gas or liquid.
Believe they may have a solid inner core. We're not sure about that.
And these are some atmospheric chemistries
that make up most of our atmosphere.
Which combines with the material on the planetary surface, and that makes
some things like krypton, xenon,
et cetera.
These are the escape velocities for the constituents.
You can see for Earth,
we have a varying escape velocity
depending on the surface temperature.
How planets gain
atmospheric gases are these three effects.
So outgassing, which I just went over, evaporation and
sublimation, and bombardment.
Outgassing,
like I said before, volcanoes expel water, carbon dioxide, molecular
nitrogen, hydrogen sulfide, and sulfur
dioxide. And shown here,
interestingly enough, is the effects of outgassing.
Let's see if I can get this little... Oops. The video's not working.
Anyway, there's a video that shows this particular
atmosphere or
asteroid called Oumuamua.
And it was interesting because it was tumbling at a rate that was
unexpected for an asteroid, and we
found out that that was due to outgassing from
some of these effects on its surface.
Evaporation and sublimation.
We just talked about liquid to gas and solid to gas.
And the bombardment. Surface materials are vaporized by comets and
asteroids.
Now, these are the chemistries of the different planets,
and I think you have a homework assignment on this.
And these are some of the atmospheric parameters,
where the surface temperature on the Earth is about 290 degrees Kelvin,
constant.
And we have the surface density included and
the scale height included here.
Atomic oxygen, GEO versus
LEO. There's really not much concern less than about
100 kilometers.
A little bit.
But as you go higher than that,
you've got UV radiation photochemically
disassociated with diatomic oxygen
and requires disassociation energy greater than
about five electron volts.
It's abundant in altitudes greater than about 60 kilometers,
atomic oxygen is.
And the mean free path is long, so the probability of
recombination or reformation of the ozone is
small.
The terminology on the right-hand side is
from the Space Weather Prediction Center.
And F10.7 refers to
solar radio flux
at
10.7 centimeters,
and that's about
2,800 megahertz.
It's called the F10.7 index, and that is a
good indication of solar parameters
at those altitudes.
It can also cause scattering and recombination.
We will focus on the chemical reactions here,
where the highly reactive nature of atomic
oxygen, combined with high-impact energy, is most
significant on the ram side or the side facing
the
constituents in space or the
direction that the satellite is traveling in.
And we get a mass loss of
this,
where Re is reaction efficiency.
It's
centimeters cube per atom.
After you go to May 18, get ready to put it in that bank if you want.
That's pleasant.
Incident atom, one cubic centimeter per incident atom.
Phi is the atomic oxygen flux in
atmosphere
Per centimeter cubed
second.
Or the number density
times the orbital
velocity.
Rho is obviously the density, and M is mass of the test
panel.
A is area, and DT is obviously change in
time. So that's kind of important.
That's your mass loss. The other thing that's important is
your thickness of the material loss, which is given by this
equation, where the atomic oxygen reacts with the
material, especially polymers,
carbons, and metals, and gradually erodes that
material.
So this is your
homework problem,
and you can estimate that using the
parameters given here. And
you will see the thickness of the Kapton
panel will
decay.
And we're using the same satellite that we did in
problems one and two.
So this is homework problem three.
Homework two, problem three.
So quantifying those effects, we have
several things going on. We got ground testing.
We can carry out ground-based test of the exposure of different
materials to atomic oxygen and measure the erosion
rate.
Number two, estimate the atomic oxygen fluence in space as
a function of altitude, worst case, solar activity, and
geographic location, taking into account the daily and
seasonal variations of the solar
UV radiation.
We can also, number three, carry out statistical analysis to
determine the degradations and compare with
other similar materials.
So physical sputtering can occur.
We have neutral particles that collide with the spacecraft
surface, and that greatly increases with
spacecraft charging. We'll talk more about that in
the plasma section.
Usually not a huge issue except with very long missions, and
there's some of them up there. There's DSCS, which is Defense
Satellite Communications System, which some of them are still
around. We've got TDRS that NASA uses for
communication, and Landsat, which NASA uses
for Earth observation.
What does it yield? It yields a lot of
oxygen. These different sputtering.
Hydrogen and helium don't have a huge effect, though.
So it's mostly atomic oxygen,
O2, nitrogen, and argon that has the biggest effects
on these materials.
Spacecraft glow
is not really well understood, but due
to the neutral environment,
mostly LEO, you can get that effect.
So if you're curious,
a Riley is a unit that
reflects one over four pi 10 to the
photons
per meter squared second
times steradian, which is a solid angular
measurement.
This is what it looks like. We got pictures from the shuttle.
The ISS is a little too large to notice,
but on the vertical stabilizer of the shuttle,
you can clearly see this effect. It also appears to depend on the
size and relative geometry,
mostly on the ram-facing side, and it affects remote
sensing observations from optical payloads and communication
because that gas is charged, and we'll learn why
later, and it interferes with the communication.
Some solutions are
to use materials not susceptible to glow,
but those materials tend to be more susceptible to
atomic oxygen.
The other thing that you can do is you can orient the sensors.
Excuse me.
Orient the sensors in what's called
the opposite side from the ram side.
And
you can put those on the other side, and it
will not have as large of an effect.
So that is called the wake side. Let me draw a little picture here.
So if the satellite
Is going this way.
This would be the ram
because the relative particles are going that way, and this would be
the wake side.
So orient those important sensors on the wake side.
Avoid Kapton alone
and silver because both are very
susceptible to atomic oxygen.
Okay. So I was going to do one last in-class
exercise,
and that was back on
this page.
And
this will be the last thing I do for tonight.
I have to add a couple more
slides.
Okay, so we're going to estimate using this equation
the erosion depth of a Kapton panel, and this will help you with homework
problem three.
So from the previous slide, we had the change in thickness
is the reaction efficiency
times
phi,
where for Kapton, you can look it up on
this.
We've got 3.1 times 10 to the minus 24
centimeter cubed per atom.
And phi
is
the atoms
per atomic oxygen atoms per centimeter
cubed times the velocity. So we know
the velocity is square root of mu over R,
so that is equal to the square root of
398600.5
kilometers cubed per second squared.
And R is 6378
plus 275 kilometers,
or
7.7403
kilometers per second.
Or,
since we need it in centimeters, that would be
centimeters per second.
So on the low side,
let's go back and see what it said. It said the atomic number
densities are 6 times 10 to the 6, 2 times 10 to the
7, and 1 times 10 to the 8. So low would be
6 times 10 to the 6
atoms
per centimeter cubed times
centimeters per second
times
3.1
times 10 to the minus 24 centimeters
cubed per atom
times 255 days, which is what we
estimated from our oversimplification
of problem one,
times 24 hours
times
3,600 seconds in an hour.
And if you calculate that, you get a low side of
3.17 micrometers.
Using the second number in this equation, you get
medium of 10 micrometers, and on the high side,
you get
micrometers.
So
part B
was if the Kapton panel has a thickness of 50
micrometers, would the satellite deorbit first with no orbital
corrections or would its panel erode
first?
It would likely deorbit first
during high solar
activities. But
if there's high solar activities, that would occur about the same
time that the Kapton panels
are corroded.
And again, how could you make this more accurate?
Again, use R
as a function
of
velocity,
as a function
of altitude.
Okay, so that is the last slide that
I was going to go over this evening.
And if anyone wants to stay on and chat or has any questions,
please let me know. So that should get you with homework problem
three.
And these are my references.
All right. Signing off. Thank you for coming to
listen to me live for the five participants that did.
And for the rest of you, enjoy the video.
See you next week.
Thank you. Have a good night. Good night.